> From: Mans Hulden <mhulden@email.arizona.edu>
> Date: 12 October 2009 03:38:17 MDT
> To: Kenneth Reid Beesley <krbeesley@gmail.com>
> Subject: Re: algorithm for =>
>
> Ken,
>
> Context restriction for single contexts A => B _ C can be compiled  
> like:
>
> [~[~[?* B] A ?* | ?* A ~[C ?*]]]
>
> But this approach is very hard to extend to the multi-context case (if
> you want the operands to be arbitrary regular languages) and grows
> into a huge regular expression as you add more contexts.
>
> For that reason, I compile context restriction differently (Anssi's
> overall method I believe is quite similar, but some of the details
> differ). Let's look at how the two-context case is compiled in foma,
> from which I think you can easily see the generalization. We compile:
>
> A => B1 _ C1 , B2 _ C2
>
> as a three-step process
>
> define One [\x* x A x \x*] - [\x* [B1 x \x* x C1 | B2 x \x* x C2]  
> \x*];
> define Two `[One,x,0];
> define Result ~Two;
>
> One defines the language where at least one instance of A occurs in a
> illegitimate context, except we have used the special symbol "x" to
> mark the substrings we are referring to, so that the illegitimate A is
> always flanked by "x" symbols. Language Two removes the marker symbols
> "x", and Result takes the complement, resulting in the language where
> A does not occur in an illegitimate context.
>
> To generalize to more contexts than two, simply add more expressions
> in the union expression in One, i.e.
>
> [\x* [B1 x \x* x C1 | B2 x \x* x C2| ... | Bn x \x* x Cn] \x*]
>
> Of course, a single-context contextual restriction is just:
>
> define One [\x* x A x \x*] - [\x* [B1 x \x* x C1] \x*];
>
> In actuality you'd want to choose some other symbol than "x" to be
> your auxiliary marker symbol. I'm using "x" just for legibility in the
> above.
>
> The above three lines should get you almost everything you want. But
> perhaps I should still say a couple of words about additional concerns
> you might have, such as:
>
> (1) empty contexts
> (2) boundaries in contexts
> (3) efficiency concerns
>
> As for (1), where you have contexts such as a => b _ , with no
> right-hand context defined, you want to compile that exactly as the
> formula above, by simply defining 0 (the empty string) as the
> non-defined contexts. In this example B1 = b, and C1 = 0, and the
> compilation proceeds exactly as I said earlier.
>
> You probably also will want to refer to boundary symbols by saying
> things like a => b | .#. _ , in which case you want to make a slight
> addition to the above method.  We can treat the boundary symbol like
> any other symbol throughout the compilation, provided we make one
> small change to the formula. The change we need to make to the above
> three-step compilation to get the actual "word edge" interpretation
> for .#. is the following:
>
> define Three [.#. \.#.* .#.] - Two;
> define Result `[Three, .#., 0];
>
> So in Three, instead of taking the complement of Two, we take the
> complement with respect to the language where every word begins and
> ends with boundary symbols. Adding the above two lines to the
> three-liner above takes care of the boundary handling in its entirety.
>
> Point (3), about efficiency, might come up if you're compiling huge
> contextual restrictions. And it is only relevant if you're using the
> "other" symbol "?" in your finite-state machines, and if that symbol
> is present in either the center of the contextual requirement A, or
> the contexts B1,...,Bn, C1, ...Cn. Anyway, in such a case it is
> prudent to make sure your special symbol "x" cannot occur in any of
> these languages, which it might, if you have ? in them. I fix it by
> simply adding "x" to the alphabet of each of these languages before
> compiling the context restriction, after which ? can never match "x".
> In xerox notation, the same thing can be done by:
>
> define C1new C1 & ~$x;
>
> and similarly for the other languages. After this, use C1new instead
> of C1, etc. when actually compiling the compound statement.
>
> This third point about efficiency is not crucial and you can safely
> ignore it for the time being. However, if you use this definition of
> context restriction in compiling rewrite rules, it might be good to
> add it at some point to be able to handle large batches of parallel
> rules. I think xfst omits this, which is why large context
> restrictions compile slower than they should. In general, allowing the
> auxiliary "x" in center languages and context languages is unnecessary
> and can cause nondeterministic state explosion in the intermediate
> results.
>
> I'm attaching the basic case as an xfst/foma-compilable script.
>
> I hope this helps. Let me know if you have any questions.
>
> Rgds,
>
> Mans
>
>
> On Sun, Oct 11, 2009 at 12:13 AM, Kenneth Reid Beesley
> <krbeesley@gmail.com> wrote:
>>
>> Hello Måns,
>>
>> Do you have an algorithm (that you're willing to share) for compiling
>> restrictions like
>>
>> whatever  =>   left  _   right
>>
>> whatever =>  left1  _  right1,  left2  _  right2, ...
>>
>> ???
>>
>> I know that the Xerox algorithm was faulty for years, until Anssi  
>> Yli-Jyrä
>> reported the problem
>> to Lauri, who fixed it.
>>
>> Thanking you in anticipation,
>>
>> Ken
>>
>> ******************************
>> Kenneth R. Beesley, D.Phil.
>> P.O. Box 540475
>> North Salt Lake, UT
>> 84054  USA
>>
